This piece, I actually created in 20, I'm trying to think of the year, but I'm pretty sure was 2017.
When I originally created it in collaboration with American Friends Service Committee, Chicago.
And we created it to create a t-shirt.
So this one was the Defender Communities Defund Police.
And then there was the Resist Surveillance Build Sanctuary, was the other piece that looks very similar to this one.
And they were made for the AFSC Chicago Program as like a fundraising tool for their youth led organizing work.
And at the time, I, you know, Defund Police was not a very common phrase that was being used in the public, right, in the mainstream conversations.
And so it was a very, it was new for me to think about what does it mean to defund the police, what does it mean to defend our communities, right?
And what does it mean to actually defund the police and breathe and then re-eninvest that money into our communities and into our what we need, right?
And so I think, you know, in this image, you see people who are sort of breaking the walls down, which represents like breaking down prison walls.
You see people, two people sort of pulling these handcuffs apart to represent, you know, defunding police, a police abolition.
You see someone with a camera, right, in 2017, we were really big into a cop watch trainings and so like documentation and, and, and watching the police.
And, and then you see, you know, another woman with her fist up, another woman with her chocolate, which is like a very like, very Mexican, like speak, like speaking to a Mexican community, which, you know, in hindsight, now I'm like, okay, the chocolate is to like, is towards the police, but I know that the chocolate can also, or the sandal can also represent discipline, right, in our communities.
But in I think the way that I created it was wanting to sort of reclaim getting away from the discipline in our communities and moving it towards like, that's what like targeting the police instead.
The am is kind of like the what do you call it like the thong, like the for the for the sandal.
Yeah, so, so some people noticed it and other people didn't, so I thought that that was, you know, another people, and then, and with art, right, there's critique, right, and so then there was this critique right from people in my community being like, but this is like a form of punishment itself, right, and I'm like, this is this that is a punitive action and I'm like, right.
And you're right, and let's like move away from that and like pointed towards point our aggression that we take out in our communities on the actual people that are causing the trauma to begin with.
Yeah, so I think, yeah, and so I think with this piece, it lived in our communities and in Chicago on t-shirts, people really fell in love with it.
And then in 2020, when the uprisings happened.
This I saw that the original piece was starting to get shared a lot from like my social media profiles, and I was like, you know what I really want to sort of like, as an artist, I really was like, my skills having, have improved from 2017 to 2020, I would like to sort of like, read your eye a little bit and maybe fix up some spots and, you know,
fully form some people's bodies and things like that. So I revisited the piece, gave it a new color scheme, and then like reshared it, and then that piece sort of went viral and was being shared all across the internet.
Which was really cool to see that and to see it finally in a different context to see it in the context beyond just our Chicago communities who were, you know, saying we should defund the police and reinvest in our communities and people sort of seeing that as this wild idea.
And then to see it being embraced on a national level of like, yes, absolutely defund the police, look at what they're doing.
And all of this money could go towards resources for our communities, which we know would actually be the way that we, you know, the way that our communities could actually thrive.
And you would see, you know, less crime, you would see less, less violence, you would see if you just understood that communities have so little money, whereas in Chicago police were receiving $4 million a day, like the police budget was like was like 40% actually it was an increase under Lori Lightfoot.
But just like being able to like use this piece as a narrative as a storytelling jumping off point to be like, yes, defund the police because we need to defend our communities because they give $4 million a day and that's absurd and our communities are struggling.
So people really resonated with that and we're like, oh, okay, then I can get I can get behind the funding of police and reinvesting that money.
And I love all the interpretations that come out of it, right, especially when maybe it was or wasn't an intention behind the while I made the art, right, but then seeing the ways that people interpret it, I'm like, yes, that's that's exactly what artists for, you know, to think into to think beyond to think of transformation to think of to like create stories within the work, right, to create the reflection of ourselves to create this.
This visible, like this visual, this visual notion of like power for so many people who feel powerless, right, like I think that that is so cool to be able to do that through through yeah a 2d piece.
So yeah, so thank you for saying that.